[SPEAKER_01]: I was thinking this whole idea of, in these times of great uncertainty, in this time of such a virus going around, these troubled times, such a difficult time, now it's time to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now it's time to practice, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the practice now?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: As if it was something different.
[SPEAKER_00]: As if it was any different before, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when things are comfortable, I don't practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when things are difficult, now you're gonna practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when I get reminded of the practice, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you kind of... Well, it's not really procrastination.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: The issue there, it's more like intoxication with the good times.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intoxication with the health.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intoxication with safety, with lack of risk, with lack of illnesses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intoxication with that whole current state of affairs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, you don't really, like, you don't make the effort to do what you know should be done, because you kind of also know that health will not last forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But while you're... that's... that's what they would refer to as intoxicated.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are intoxicated with health, with youth, with life, because you genuinely think like a drunk person, who, when he's drunk, he's invincible.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows it's not true, but he doesn't... he doesn't feel like it's not true.
[SPEAKER_00]: It feels like it's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like this... this is... this state... ah, great, I'll...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll have to seize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll make most of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, you don't actually... you lose... you voluntarily lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot lose perspective there, and you can ask yourself, OK, I am healthy now, but can that change?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: The answer is immediate.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm alive now, but can that change?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Another immediate answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that answer requires maintenance.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to keep, sort of, keep keeping up with that context, because it's too easy to ignore, because it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, sorry, it's unpleasant to keep looking at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I could get sick.
[SPEAKER_00]: I could get, like, you know, I could die.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, my youth, my strength is fading.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't measure how much, but it has to.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's easier to not think about it, especially because you don't see any drawback in not thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why we have to instruct monks and people to make the effort to start seeing the drawbacks in these things, which will then keep you in check.
[SPEAKER_00]: But without it, without making that effort, you're not going to see the drawbacks.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, it's kind of... when things are difficult, you do want to practice more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because now you see a drawback.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, now you see... Now it's thrown in your face.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if it's too difficult, there's no possibility of... Well... ...settling down and thinking... More often... yeah, more often than not, it's kind of too late, if you waited until, okay, now you're really sick, that's it, and now you want to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's a bit...
[SPEAKER_00]: You shouldn't have left it that far.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the Buddha again would tell monks to basically withdraw themselves and live in seclusion and make the effort less to regret it later on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the time will come where it will be too late for the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't do anything about it, because it's just too much to bear, or simply your health is gone now, and you're just in constant pain, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to prepare beforehand, with wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Well, that's what wisdom is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Foreseeing things before they occur.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want... you want to practice restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But...
[SPEAKER_01]: Good restraint, not just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Blind restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you get a bit of a pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Celibacy is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, that pain, that discomfort, will keep you on the edge, to keep you... See, that pain is in your own control.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pain is in your own control.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: What the Buddha referred to is known, called as pain of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's up to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You choose to renounce things on account of which you experience that pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you start developing wisdom, you realize pain is not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: There has to be pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only choice you have, it's not like whether you're not going to have any pain, it's whether it's going to be on your own terms or not on your own terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you replace the pain of household life, as the Buddha said, as in the pain of sensuality, gain, loss, praise, blame, all these worldly wins, you would replace those pains with pains of restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you see, ah, when I have pains of restraint, I can't have the pains of household life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And these pains of restraint are not actually pains from the point of view of the pains of household life.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're easy to bear.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not painful, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have the same amount of pressure in needing to get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's if you develop wisdom on account of restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, of course, restraint will be overwhelming you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you... it's... the only reason that it's overwhelming you is because the mind is too weak to bear it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind still acts out of the assumption that I must be free from pain at all cost.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as there is this body, there will be pain arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, for as long as there is this body, there will be pleasure arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then again, you replace the pleasure of the household life, pleasure of sensuality, eating whenever you want, all these things, you replace it with the pleasure of renunciation, with freedom that comes from it, with burdenlessness of it, complete lack of pressure, like genuine, like lightness, like there's absolutely nothing you do... you have to do, you don't need to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the... the sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Worldly benefit as well of doing that, say, eating once a day and choosing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: While you've got plenty of food, you could eat all day if you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you choose not to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that when there's a time of famine, when it's difficult to get food, then... Well, you'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't even need to think like with some doomsday scenario at the back of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just want to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I have an option.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll either have this comfort on account of my own
[SPEAKER_00]: Well-reasoned will and intention and choice, or I have a discomfort on account of my own unrestrained desire that controls me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is... which pain is better?
[SPEAKER_00]: Which pain is less risky?
[SPEAKER_00]: Which pain is less wild?
[SPEAKER_00]: Which pain is less likely to result in greater unpleasant repercussions?
[SPEAKER_00]: In you saying no and restraining yourself, or in you saying yes and riding that wild desire for wherever it takes you, scratching your itch like a maniac, which one do you think is going to result in worse states of mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: You already know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody knows that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not overnight you will be celibate and never eat again, but you need to adopt that as a value, that your desires need to be restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: And your desires are not rooted in these random things in beautiful sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're rooted in your own intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you will learn where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said, man's sensuality is not the beautiful things in the world that he can see or taste or touch.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's his thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where sensuality is rooted.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you'll never get to see the roots of that sensuality if you never restrain your own actions and your own senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's again exactly another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to wait until it's too late, until your senses start decaying and so on, in order to practice that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, if you wait, then it will be too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you did not, if you could not restrain your senses while they were still relatively young and operating normally, basically, while the domains of those senses were clear to you,
[SPEAKER_00]: Sights were clear, pleasures for the sights were clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not gonna restrain it when it's all gone, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you become senile and you can't see well, you can't hear well, everything is uncomfortable, everything is just too much weight on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you had an option to exercise strength and develop strength, you didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the bare minimum that's required for you to start developing strength, it's too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you waited too long.
[SPEAKER_00]: The same for health, life, anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you don't want to wait till it's too long.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if sometimes you get complacent, like, because, you know, sometimes there's nothing bothering you, you're kind of practicing, so you don't feel necessarily guilty that you're lazy or procrastinating, but, you know, you are getting complacent, you maybe have trouble seeing where the problem is, well, just maybe turn up your restraint or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the pain will come.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's your work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, am I resisting this pain?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I fearing this pain?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I trying to justify my actions to get rid of this pain?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or am I genuinely in war?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because this is not a pain that harms me, by the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Saying no to smell, sight, smell, taste, touches, doesn't harm you at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, there is no threat, no danger in saying no to not look at something, in saying no to not taste something.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is really nothing dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, it's the worst type of pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, because the mind and the senses are used to going wherever desire wants to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like catching a wild dog.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be kicking and screaming and trying to bite your face off, if you tie down first time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because in its mind, it's fighting for its life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's actually safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's actually exactly, yeah, this is the... yeah, that's the safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he doesn't recognize it's such.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once he calms down, then he gets to recognize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, once it's completely tame, then it's tame, then it's fixed.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, the Buddha compared your own mind and senses exactly always to wild animals, to the big independent bull elephant that you have to catch and then strap down with the big sort of chains and leather belts until it... basically until it calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it will listen to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to restrain your senses and then eventually they will listen to you, not you to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, sometimes these things like people can get reminders of, oh, health is a, you know, a precarious thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can quickly change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Life is precarious thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever were to inspire you to practice in the right direction, that have the right type of contemplation, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's good.
[SPEAKER_00]: But...
[SPEAKER_00]: You can also find that inspiration within yourself and not wait to be prompted externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because more often than not, the external prompts means it's too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like there, there were some cases in the suttas who had external prompts.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a result of that, they made the effort and purified their mind completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I think those cases are far fewer in number, which is why we still talk about them today.
[SPEAKER_00]: Two millennia later.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, they were so profound, you know, the inspirational stories, that that's why you still remember them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But far fewer than the actual... the ones they were not.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, they were facing these adverse circumstances and had no direction of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, as you're saying, you're there, like, foresight is wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Foresight is wisdom, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is, having a perspective on...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having a better, greater perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Elevated ground.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you find a way to climb onto the elevated ground and you see perspective is farther reaching from here than if I come down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I have an option.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll either come down and enjoy whatever fruit grows at the bottom of this hill, but I won't see any danger coming, because I've been toxicating, chasing down berries and apples.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or I can perhaps, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: I have my expectations in terms of providing objects for my sense desires, but then stay in the place of safety, from which I can see the danger coming from far, far, far beyond.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all within, like within everyone's mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like even now, yeah, I might not see the end of this day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if nothing happens to you, your heart might stop, as we said that before, in those talks on maraṇasati.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you realize, okay, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to... so what do I do?
[SPEAKER_00]: What you do is, don't lose perspective that your heart might stop by the end of the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all you need to do is protect that perspective, everything else will come out of it, naturally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-desire will come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-hatred will come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-distraction will come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Peace will come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the only reason people don't live in peace is because they keep disturbing themselves by allowing their own senses to drag them left and right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, imagine you get a big dog on a leash.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's stronger than you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it sees a rabbit or a squirrel.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're tied to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be very painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you have... doesn't matter how big the dog is, if it's trained, and if at the slightest sort of tightness of the leash it will stop, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not threatened.
[SPEAKER_00]: And many people know implicitly that if circumstances were to change and they were to be pushed to the limits due to circumstances, due to sensuality, ill-will or something happening, they have implicit sort of recognition of the fear that they will completely lose control.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's frightening.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no idea where you're gonna end up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And sometimes people, yeah, end up where they don't want to end up, on account of just careless decisions and choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all of that is rooted in not having that fundamental perspective on your own situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is rooted in presently, basically, enduring intoxication.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's, that's the, like, a basis of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think you will live forever, you will be healthy forever,
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will be sort of... your senses will be operating properly, strongly, clearly, forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you'll be... you're never gonna age, never gonna go decrepit.
[SPEAKER_00]: And these little reminders of the perspective would be much more apparent and much more self-evident if people would spend their most of the time within the renunciation and sense restraint, not within sensuality and desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: You lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha called, basically, sensuality and other hindrances, the weakness of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as we compare the wisdom to that elevated ground from which you have a better perspective, well, this is literally dragging you down.
[SPEAKER_00]: You keep coming down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, you lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, obviously, if you constantly live on the lower planes, you'll never get the perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or if you had it, you lost it completely, so you need to retrace your steps and go back up.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what I'm saying is people don't go back up, do not go back to the wiser perspective, because they keep choosing centrality, choosing desire, choosing scratch and itch.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't choose it, you're automatically climbing up the hill on a higher ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then there's this idea that by sort of teasing those hindrances, you learn to, you know, you're challenging those hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Teasing the hindrances?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're practicing with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's like you're teasing a wild crocodile.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Teasing a wild hyena.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you get stronger.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the result of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just gonna basically get you in worse when it gets you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're in a battle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't train a dog by teasing it to be wild.
[SPEAKER_00]: You train it by calming it down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, only person basically... You know who would say you tease it?
[SPEAKER_00]: The one who couldn't calm it down.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was too weak to calm an animal down, and then we try to make its own way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not supposed to calm your senses down.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're supposed to tease them out, because there's nothing else that I can do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're supposed to run with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Run with them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Run alongside the wild dog.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, why don't you try that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, actually get a wild dog.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then you've...
[SPEAKER_00]: Tie yourself to it, and try running, and see how far you get, before you end up being dragged against your will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if that's going to be that hard for a wild dog, random wild animal, imagine how bad it's going to be if you do that to your own senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, it's based on a presumption that you can run.
[SPEAKER_00]: What if you can't run anymore?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know when people depend on constantly having something to do, activity, engagement, projects, give meaning to their life.
[SPEAKER_00]: It basically helps them float.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if they are left alone, even for half a day, without company, without engagement, without talking, they start losing their mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, now there is nothing to run along with, to keep you occupied.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are left with the nature of that thing and you realize, oh my goodness, this is terrifying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it can rip you apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: If one animal runs to the left, the other animal runs to the right,
[SPEAKER_00]: Which one do you want to follow?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you have six animals, by the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Six senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, which one do you run with?
[SPEAKER_00]: All six of them?
[SPEAKER_00]: How's that possible?
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to live with the wild animals or...?
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to live with the wild animals and at the same time pretend they are not wild.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, close yourself in the room with a crocodile, hyena, wild macaques or any chimpanzee or something and see how well that will go.
[SPEAKER_01]: See how peaceful it... How peaceful that will be, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's why it's not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: Calming your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Restraining your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, oh, I can do away with this, because I got this magic, magic technique for my meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no meditation without sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to start meditation, you start sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is your meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meditation will come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once the animals come, like these ones, and sit next to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're in charge of them, they're not in charge of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's your own senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I will not look at that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I will not say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I will not go after that sense of touch.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unpleasant, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I choose this discomfort on account of far worse discomfort of a rabid mind being dragged left and right by those same senses that you were trying to appease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's good for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's good to have...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, you want to do what's good for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just...
[SPEAKER_00]: One person acts out of no real perspective on what's really good for you, and then another person develops perspective on what's really good for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, actually, feeding the wild animal when it's in its fit of madness, it's not good for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, it calms it down for a second, but makes it even wilder, because now it associates that wild behavior with reward.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I don't reward the wild behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: I reward peaceful behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how... that's how to train yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You reward peaceful behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the reward?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's that, basically, recognition.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, are we still talking about the simile or about you, yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, slightly different.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, it's like reward...
[SPEAKER_00]: In your own case, say, in terms of the sense restraint, the reward is absence of desire now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you keep increasing the desire, in the same sense you would increase the
[SPEAKER_00]: The madness of an animal, by scratching it, by teasing it, by feeding it, by giving it more, when it wants more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, initially, it hurts to say no, but after a while, desire disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you stop scratching your itch, you stop it, like freeing yourself from addiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't be going back to that which you were addicted, when you're free from addiction, when there's no desire towards it, and then you recognize that whole relief.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm free from that big pressure of that desire, because I endured away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you won't go back to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you will, if you completely lose wisdom again, if you completely lose perspective, if you completely stop recognizing that that's much better for you, and much more pleasurable, actually, to not engage in that wild, mad addiction, whatever else, craving, desire, satisfaction, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the absence of that pressure is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just that it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: The absence of that pressure is the only reason you give in to the pressure, because you want it to go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now you found a direct way that doesn't involve giving in, that doesn't involve being dragged around by a wild animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: You found a direct way of removing the pressure, basically deflating it, depressuring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the pleasure renunciation that's loftier than any other pleasure you can experience in this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you have too much of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that pleasure, as the Buddha said, pleasure of jhāna, basically, that's what we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasure of renunciation, which is the pleasure of jhāna, you can't... there is no craving for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the result of you saying no to your craving, sufficiently long enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then... and the Buddha realized.
[SPEAKER_00]: He asked himself, oh, is this... why am I afraid of this pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Should I be afraid of these pleasures?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is nothing unwholesome underlying this pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, I won't be afraid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll cultivate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you cultivate pleasure of renunciation, at the same time, you cannot cultivate pleasure towards sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you cultivate pain of renunciation, pain of elements, pain of withdrawal, you cannot have the pain of household life, pain of losing your children, pain of losing your wealth, pain of, like, like, whatever, abuse, anything else that people can suffer and encounter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't apply to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind is already far, far withdrawn from that domain.